Hey everybody, welcome to
the content video going
over section 5.2, lists.
So there's quite a bit to
cover in this section, but
I'll try to keep it brief.
Lists are definitely one
of the more powerful tools.
Built-in lists in Python
are a powerful tool that you
can use while you're building
out code and algorithms.
There's a lot to them and a lot
to know. So again, we're going to
try and cover most of that in
this video, but we'll probably be
brief with every little thing. So
this is definitely something that
you're going to want to try and
practice on your own if it's not
something that you're getting. So
what is a list? It's a sequence
of values, typically comma
separated, that you store data with
in Python. So a list typically
looks like this. Here's a list C,
and it looks like it's just
a couple of integers, right?
It's good to note here
that lists usually store
homogeneous data, which means
data is all the same type.
um rather than heterogeneous data
and that is it's kind of just best
practice to store the same type of
data in your list it is possible to
store data of different types in a
list so like this list right here
stores a student's name their gpa
and the year that they're out that
their graduation year so it is
possible but it's better practice to
store data all of the same type and
there are better data structures to
store heterogeneous data that we'll
learn about later in this course.
And those data types are
things like dictionaries or
JSON. So best practice for
lists, same type of data.
All right, so how do we access
elements of a list? So let's
say we've got all this data, we
want to do something with it.
This is where we start indexing lists.
And this is a really important
graphic. I'll try and zoom in here for
you guys. So here's a list. This is
the exact same list we were looking
at very first. So there are five
elements in the list as you can see,
but the list starts indexing or
starts counting from zero. So that's
just a computer science programming
thing is that everything starts counting
from zero and that's why we get
a lot of what we call off by one
errors is when we expect something to
be a certain number and it's actually
one off of that because we forgot
computers start counting at zero.
And so you can see that
negative 45 is in the
zeroth position, 6 is
in the first position,
0 is in the second position,
72 in the third, and 1543 in
the fourth position. But this
list has a length of 5, so
that's kind of where things,
again, get kind of confusing.
There's a built-in function that
you can use to see how long a list
is, so it's just called len, and that
will output the length of a list.
If you wanted to output a single
variable from a list or a single
value, you could print out the name
of that list along with brackets
and the index of that particular
thing in the list, or sorry, the
index of that value in the list.
We'll do some examples of this in a
second. So if you're kind of lost,
just stick with me for a second.
Another really important concept that
doesn't get talked about a
lot is that lists are mutable
or changeable, whereas
other things like sequences,
strings, tuples, those are immutable,
so they can't be modified. So
what do I mean by that? I mean, if
I have a list of all the ages of
everybody in this class, and then
somebody new joins the class, I can add
a new age to that list. Or let's
say somebody drops it, or somebody
has a birthday. I can go in and I
can change that data to update it so
that it reflects reality. Whereas
if I have a string like my first
name, Chelsea, I can't change the
variable that stores that string or I
guess I can change the variable but
I can't change that string itself.
If I want to change the string I
actually just create a new string.
So like let's say that I don't
know I updated the spelling
of my name to instead of be S
-E-A, I wanted it to be S-E-Y.
I would be creating a new string
even if I like went and like said
to the string, hey, lop off the A
at the end of my name and make it
a Y instead. That string will
always bounce back. It will always
revert back to the original way
that it was. So if I wanted to store
that changed string, I actually
just created an entirely new one.
So lists are changeable.
They can be modified.
Strings and other things like
tuples are not changeable.
And I think that's everything I
wanted to go over from the textbook.
So let's, oh yeah, we'll do some
examples of foreign range. So
yeah, let's go and jump into
our code space and actually code
a couple of examples so we can
see what's going on with lists.
Okay, let's do an example where
we've got last stages. I think that's
a pretty good example. So let's say
we've got all sorts of ages, 41,
52,
we've got a 21 year old, a 22 year old,
19,
65, and we'll throw in another
22 year old. That's great.
Just a variety of ages. So this
is kind of how you create a list.
You just enclose your data with
brackets and you can put any type
of data and list, and you just
separate the values by commas. Okay,
so what can I do with this
with these ages? Well, I could
index my list. So let's say I
wanted to access the element 21.
That's in the 1, 2, 3, sorry
I can't count, 1, 2, 3, the
third position in my list, but
I remember that lists count
from 0, so 0, 1, 2, so it's
actually in the second position
in my list. So I could print
out class ages at the index 2.
And that should give me
the age 21, as you can see
right there. Let me clear
this terminal up a little bit.
Okay, so there it is, 21.
Similarly, I could print out class
ages at the index 0, or maybe
if I wanted to get the last
element of my list, I could do the
negative 1th index, which will
give me the very last thing in my
list. So it's zero, or sorry, the
second index gave me 21, the zeroth
index gave me 41, and then the
last element of my list is 21.
There are times when we might not
know the length of our list, and we
don't want to hard code values in,
and so if we wanted to access the
very last element, negative one's
a great way to do that. Because
what if I add something new into my
list? Well, the negative one is still
just going to give me the last
element of my list. So it's going to
give me 90 now. It's not hard-coded
to give me this specific value.
Okay, so that's a little bit of
indexing. And we've mentioned that
we use for loops a lot to iterate
through a list. So if I wanted
to iterate through this list, I
could say for age in class ages.
And I don't know what I might
want to do here, but maybe
maybe everybody had a birthday
and I need to update my ages so I
could say age equals well I guess
age plus equals one print age
and uh there they all
are 42 53 22 23 20 66
23 and 91 so everybody
had a birthday that's
that's my new data set um this
okay I want to I don't know if I
want to get into this too deeply
in this video but let's say we
had a list of ages and well I guess
let me let me show you something
Maybe this is what I'll do. So
let's say that we have a variable
called i, and i we're just
going to set that equal to zero.
What we could do is we could say
for age in class ages brings out
class ages at index i,
and then add one to i.
Okay, so what is this code doing?
And maybe I want you to ask
yourself that as you're watching.
What does class ages at index
i give us? Well, index i is just
pointing to a variable zero.
and so class ages at i should just
give us the zero with index of
our list right and then we increase
i by one so i becomes one and then
that should give us the next index
of our list over and over and
over again so if i was to print out
this you can see it's just going
to print out all the ages in my
loop or sorry in my list so then
what's the difference between doing
that and just printing out age.
Well, in this context, there is no
difference. They're printing out
the same data, and you can see
we're just getting doubles of that
now in our output terminal. So
what's the benefit? Well, there are
a lot of cases where this could
be beneficial. Like, let's say you
wanted to grab an index of a
value before or after your current
index. So let's say I wanted to get
class ages plus one and if I was to
print that well I get an error but
ignore that for now so the first
time I run my loop class ages at
zero plus one is gonna give me
one so it's gonna go and pull the
first index which is 52 and then
age is 41 so you can see it printed
out both of those maybe I should
add some commentary very sphere
so you can tell what's going on a
little bit clearer.
Okay also still ignore the error
message. So we've got class age at
index i is 52 but age is 41 and
then class age at index i is 21 and
then age is 52. So index i is one
step ahead or one iteration ahead
kind of than the age variable is.
But check out what happens when
I try to do the same thing to age.
So if I say print out age plus
one, that's not pulling an index,
that's just going to literally add
one to my age, which is what I
did here. So that's actually not
what I want to do. So using an
iterator variable outside of our loop
to grab indexes in our list can
be really helpful if there are
specific reasons to be getting the
variables around our iterator variable.
That's a lot of terminology, so
hopefully that all makes sense.
Okay, and to wrap this
up, we'll just do one more
example. This will be
simpler, so a list of strings.
Let's say we've got favorite
colors, and obviously all
of our favorite colors are
Aggie blue, fighting white,
and we don't have favorite
colors after that, pink,
okay? So we could loop through our
list of colors, so for color in fav
colors, whoops, and of course we
can print out each of the colors one
at a time let me add some documentation
and that's perfect and if we
were to run this we still get an
error let me comment out uh this line
of code because that's what's breaking
okay aggie blue fighting white
and pink now this is what i wanted to
show you guys so we have an iterator
variable here called color, all
right? Color is going to point to
each of the elements of our list one at a
time as we iterate
through the list, but then
color is a string, right? It's Aggie
blue, then fighting white, then
pink, and strings behave pretty
similar to list in a lot of regards.
um so I could iterate through a
string after I iterate through
a list so if I'm iterating
through a list of strings I could
do a nested for loop so for
letter in color print out letter
all right so what's going on here
is we're creating an iterator
variable to iterate through my list
so color becomes aggie blue and
then I'm saying well take that
aggie blue string and I actually
want to loop through that and print
out each of the letters in it.
So if I was to run this code,
I would expect to see each of
the letters one at a time along
with the outer loop printing
out the actual item of the list.
So hopefully this wasn't too
long and hopefully that made
some sense regarding lists and
indexing. We'll talk more about
lists and what you can do with
them in more in future content
videos. Thanks for watching.